It’s crazy when you think about all of
the different kinds of foods we eat.
We just swallow and hope
it all works out for the best.
Well, as it turns out,
there are better ways to think about keeping
our bodies humming healthfully along.
Welcome to the
Nutrition Facts Podcast,
I’m your host,
Dr. Michael Greger.
There are some
persistent myths about celery
and today we take them on.
In our first story,
NutritionFacts Senior Research
Scientist Kristine Dennis asks:
can celery, a vegetable
relatively high in sodium,
lower blood pressure?
Some plants may help us
reduce high blood pressure
and celery may be one of them.
But celery also contains relatively
high levels of sodium for a vegetable—
about 100 mg of sodium in one cup
(~130 g) of chopped celery.
Even though it's relatively
high in sodium,
it also contains other compounds
like NBP,
the compound primarily responsible
for celery's taste and aroma,
which can relax
the smooth muscles
that line blood vessels,
potentially resulting
in lower blood pressure.
And there are other
compounds in celery
that likely have
antihypertensive effects,
but those are all based
on rodent studies—
and indeed,
celery seed appears
to lower blood pressure
in hypertensive rats.
But what about humans?
You don't know until you put
celery seed to the test,
or in this case,
celery seed extract,
in a randomized, triple-blind,
placebo-controlled,
cross-over, clinical trial.
After four weeks of taking
the celery seed extract,
systolic blood pressure dropped
by at least 10 points
and diastolic blood pressure
by about 8 points.
But the whole celery seed
equivalent would be way more
than people could eat.
Is there anything a
more modest sprinkle
of celery seed a day
might help with?
"Treatment of women's
sexual dysfunction
using celery seed
(Apium graveolens):
A double-blind, randomized,
placebo-controlled
clinical trial."
And this study used
a culinary-friendly dose
of celery seed—
about 500 mg.
That's about ¼ tsp per capsule,
three times per day.
At the end of six weeks,
there was
a significant improvement
in the self-reported
sexual functioning
among those eating celery seeds,
with significant improvements
across multiple measures
within just three weeks.
What about celery juice?
There was a case
report of a man
who juiced a bunch
of celery every day
and had a drop
in blood pressure
and what appeared to be a
nonrandomized controlled trial
in which an undisclosed amount
of celery juice seemed to help.
A review concluded
that celery can be considered
an antihypertensive agent,
but the quality of evidence
seems slight.
What's the downside though?
Well, celery seed
is generally considered safe,
and a safety evaluation
was performed
in the blood pressure trial
that indicated so,
but maybe not for everybody.
Here is a case report
of someone who had been taking
about two tablespoons
of dried celery leaves a day,
and it seemed to cause overactive
thyroid gland activity;
the same happened
to this woman,
who had been taking celery
extract powder for weight loss.
She did lose 57 pounds (26 kg)
in 78 days
but that was likely because
the celery extract
led to hyperthyroidism.
That is not a healthy way
to lose weight,
risking side effects with names
like thyrotoxic paralysis.
Celery is also
an allergen for some,
often called
"pollen-related food allergy."
People who are allergic
to some pollens
are more likely to have
an allergy to celery,
such as what happened
in this rare case
of severe anaphylactic shock
after consumption
of raw celery.
Some only get allergic reactions
to celery
if they eat it
before exercising.
Heating celery eradicates
symptoms for about 50 percent
of people with a celery allergy,
but those who react
to raw celery also react
when it's dried.
Even if you don't have
a celery allergy,
a warning for those
who eat a lot of celery,
celery juice, or celeriac,
also known as celery root.
There are compounds
called psoralens
in the celery/parsnip/
parsley family
that can make you
sensitive to sunlight.
Farmworkers can suffer
from a condition
known as celery blisters,
when handling plants without
skin protection in the sun.
Even grocery store workers
who go from the produce aisle
to the tanning salon
can get into trouble.
These compounds can make
their way into our skin
from the inside out as well,
and they are not
destroyed by cooking.
Too much time in the sun after
commencing a "celery soup diet"
or spending time
on a tanning bed
an hour after eating
just one large celery root
may be enough to result
in a serious blistering burn.
Finally today,
is it true there are foods like celery
that take more calories to
digest than they provide?
What are some
dietary strategies
for the prevention and
treatment of obesity?
Large portion sizes
are often targeted,
and so restriction
of portion size
is an important element
of many diet programs,
but it’s hard to get
people to eat less food.
A more effective approach
may be to shift the emphasis
from the quantity
of food eaten
to the quality of
the food eaten.
By choosing foods with
lower calorie density,
we can eat the same
amount of food,
or even more food,
while losing weight.
Are there foods with
negative calories,
foods that take more energy to
digest than they provide?
Does eating celery,
for example,
result in negative
energy balance?
Celery is a readily
available whole-food
that has the ability to add
bulk and flavor to a meal,
without adding
excess calories.
It’s also subject to
a renowned health myth,
that when consuming celery
there is a ‘negative’
intake of calories
and therefore the energy
required for its digestion,
assimilation and nutrient
storage is assumed
to be greater than the
energy it itself contains.
So they put it
to the test.
A cup of celery—
about two stalks—
has 16 calories.
To digest that much celery
takes about 14 calories.
So no, the consumption
of celery does not
induce a negative
energy balance,
but you are only left
with two calories.
This fact combined with the
high fiber and water content
of celery, does make
it a good snack
for inclusion in a diet for
weight loss or management.
Maybe negative calorie foods
is not a myth after all, though.
Researchers at Penn State offered
people a meal of pasta,
in which they could eat
as much as they wanted.
If in addition to the
all-you-can-eat pasta meal
they gave people
a small salad,
what do you
think happened?
Did those 50 extra
calories of salad
just end up on top of
the pasta calories?
No, they ended up eating
less pasta over all,
and not just 50 calories
less pasta,
65 less calories,
and by adding
a bigger salad,
ended up eating a
100 fewer calories.
So effectively, the salad
provided “negative calories.”
They ate a salad on top
of what else they were eating.
They ate more food and ended
up with less calories in their system,
because it bulked up their
stomachs so much.
Of course it depends
what kind of salad.
They’re not talking about
your typical commercially
available salads with like
ranch dressing and cheese.
You add those
kinds of salad
and you end up
eating less pasta,
but there are so many calories
in conventional salads
you end up worse off
calorie-wise in the end.
But healthy
salads worked.
They conclude: “eat less” is
not always the best advice
for foods very low
in energy density,
such as water-rich
vegetables—like salad.
Larger portions
increase satiety,
the feeling of
fullness,
and reduce meal
calorie intake.
Visit nutritionfacts.org/audio to see
all of the podcast episodes
with descriptions that include
links to their associated videos.
Sources cited and other details are
available on each video's page.
Information about my books—
How Not to Die, How Not to Diet,
and How Not to Age—
is at nutritionfacts.org/books.
As always, all proceeds from
book sales go to charity.
And sign up for our free newsletter
at nutritionfacts.org/subscribe
to stay updated on the latest
bite-sized videos and articles.
NutritionFacts.org is a
science-based non-profit,
and everything on
the website is free.
There are no ads, no corporate
sponsorships, no kickbacks.
Strictly non-commercial,
not selling anything.
I just put up as a public service,
as a labor of love,
as a tribute to my grandmother
whose own life was saved
with evidence-based nutrition.
Thanks for listening.